Claude Design is here, and I'm sure
you've seen all the fun demos like how
to make an animated globe or a game.
But, the question I care about is where
does Claude Design actually fit in our
real work of building real products for
real customers?
So, I spent some time with it, and my
first impressions are Well, I have two.
One is that I don't really see how it
fits into a real workflow for
production. But, at the same time, I
think it's a breakthrough that unlocks
some use cases that weren't actually
possible before. So, let me show you,
and I'll explain what I mean.
All right. So, I'm here in Claude
Design, and I'll start with the first
use case that I tried it for. Probably
most of us are going to try to use
Claude Design for. And that is to see
where Claude Design could fit into the
process of building a new application,
bringing it to life, building it, and
shipping it. So, let's try that and see
where we end up. So, I'm going to start
a new prototype. So, let's go with a
high-fidelity mock-up, and let's build a
t-shirt marketplace. So, I really like
this out of the gate because it's like a
a big canvas. We have our familiar
prompt uh agent interface on the left.
Obviously, it's very visual. So, let's
get into it. So, I will just start with
a prompt here. I want to build a new
marketplace website application for a
community to design and sell and rate
t-shirt designs. All right. Let's send
that off and uh see how it get started
here. So, it's a familiar agent
interface. So, it's obviously running uh
some form of Claude code in this harness
here. And then we get into This is one
of my favorite aspects of Claude Design
and using Claude products in general is
this idea of asking the user questions,
shaping the direction, and really
getting to a better plan for your design
project. You know, what's the starting
point for this? Uh we're going to start
fresh. What's the aesthetic direction?
Um I don't know. Let's go playful indie
craft. Which screens should this cover?
I don't know. Decide for me. All right.
So, I'm just going to sort of choose
some of these selections here. All
right. I'm going to hit continue. Okay.
So, again, pretty familiar interface.
Here on the left, it's creating a to-do
list. This looks like Claude code or
Claude co-work. It's all kind of the
same harness, but kind of wrapped in a
different interface here. This one
obviously is much more visual. Now, you
know, the thing that I want to be clear
about here is we're not going to be
judging it on its quality. I mean, I
guess we naturally will, but in my
experience with Claude Design and Claude
code, you're really going to get the
same level of design quality either way,
no matter which tool you're using
because again, this clearly is Claude
code under the hood. So, it really comes
down to the level of detail and
direction that we put into the prompt
itself. That combined with uh whatever
model it's it's working on. Now, I don't
know if Claude Design has some special
design sauce baked into the harness.
Maybe there's a little bit of that going
on. But, in my early tests with it, I I
didn't see a big difference between just
using Claude code with some skills and
and direction and specs to generate my
designs versus what I can generate in
Claude Design itself. But, there are
some interesting capabilities of Claude
Design that I'll get into a little bit
later in this video. For now, let's see
how we go with designing a new
application. Okay. So, it did take, you
know, a a good bit of time, at least 10,
12 minutes or so to get to this point,
but here we go. It sort of pops up this
marketplace, which actually looks pretty
good on its on its first take, I must
say. It's got a pretty good vibe to it
overall. Oh, actually, most of this
stuff is functional. That's cool. Even
the sorting and the colors. Wow. At
least the front end is uh is is mostly
built. So, that's kind of cool. Now, I
do really like this concept of tweaks.
So, you can turn tweaks on and off. And
what that basically is are the Claude
agent sort of decided on what should be
the things that I might want to tweak in
the design or make some decisions on
like, you know, which font are we going
to use for the headlines? What should
the accent color be? Which actually
means that it coded these options into
the design itself. That might be fine
for mock-up purposes, but I don't know
that we want to have the this tweaking
code or logic built into the actual
design files and the code base
ultimately. So, I'm not even sure if
that's going to make it in. I I assume
that it will if we were to export all
the code. That's something to keep in
mind. Interesting is we can change that
color there. These options will differ
based on whatever it is that you're
designing. So, all of this is dynamic
and like generated by the agent, which
is pretty cool actually. Now, here is
where I think there is a bit of a
disconnect and where I really question
how useful this is in like a real
production setting of bringing a new
application to life. Because what's
going to happen next, right? We've got
this mock-up, but ultimately, how do I
use this? How do I start to build this
out into a real application? Now, we
have the share button up here, and there
are some interesting options, right? We
can download and export this as a PDF.
That's sort of like a picture of of the
mock-up. We can send it out to Canva.
I'm not going to use Canva to build an
an app. I can export as a standalone
HTML, which could be useful, or I can
hand off to Claude code. Now, handing
off to Claude code was my first
intention because, you know, we have
this design. Now, I want to actually
build it and and get into the
nitty-gritty details, right? So, if I
were to do hand off to Claude code, it
gives us this. It has a URL that points
into this design project. So, if I were
to copy this and jump into Claude code
and paste, you know, this is where I
feel a little bit of a disconnect from
my normal process of designing and
building and shipping an app, right?
Because if I were to just, you know,
have Claude code churn on this, it can
like pull down the assets that we've
designed here, but this is not a spec.
This is not a plan. I didn't give it any
instructions on exactly how we want to
wire up a back end or architect the user
experience or break it out into
milestones or anything like that. All
I'm doing is like saying like, here's a
mock-up.
Figure something out. Like, that to me
is a disconnect in the workflow. It's
not a question of the design quality.
I'm actually pretty happy with this
overall, or at least it's a good start
for something like this. But, I like I
don't even really know what it's doing
right now. Like, [laughter] what what
are we working on? It I guess it's just
going to implement the design. We We
haven't even chosen a tech stack. We
haven't even chosen a framework or
anything, right? I'm just going to stop
that for now. I mean, the the other
alternative to be a little bit more
granular about it would be to download
the actual files, right? Like, these are
these are actual code files. Looks like
React components. But, again, like I had
no decision-making process into how
these are developed. Are they going to
integrate with my code base? What is my
tech stack? What is my application? You
know, what if I already have Tailwind
installed in my application? This gave
me some generic styles.css. So, how are
we going to reconcile that? There's no
instruction. There's There's no There's
no pre-written prompt or process for
integrating this actual design into a
real code base that's in development.
For that use case of designing something
real and then building it out based on
the actual design from Claude Design, I
I probably wouldn't fit it into my
workflow, at least not today. But, there
are some other things that I would use
it for. Let me look at another one right
now. So, the other common use case, of
course, maybe even more common is that
you already have an established website
or application, and you might want to
use Claude Design to extend the design
of your existing site, maybe add new
pages, add new features, while keeping
the same design system intact. So, this
week I'm actually working on a complete
redesign of the Builder Methods site and
and the uh membership dashboard and
everything. And so, I'm actually really
happy with how it's coming out, but I
ended up designing and building most of
it inside Claude code. So, to give this
use case a try in in Claude Design,
Claude Design has this idea of design
systems. You can go in here, and if I
were to create a new design system, I
can give it a description. But, what I
did was I actually just linked to my
private GitHub repo for the new Builder
Methods site. And then I let it churn on
that for a while, and I ended up with
this design system. So, as you can see,
it it went through a long process of
analyzing my GitHub repos and analyzing
all of the code and the files and the
CSS and the fonts and the colors that I
have baked into the code base there, and
it built out this design system. So,
it's pretty extensive, and I would say
it's somewhat accurate. It gives me all
these different like typography, and
then we've got the colors. It's all
accurate. Like, these are actually the
colors that it pulled out of the CSS and
things that I'm using. It found some
notes on spacing. I mean, this
background is not actually how it works
on the actual site, but found some notes
on radius. Okay. So, like, basically,
it's just like regurgitating all of the
styles that it found in my code base.
Interesting. Kind of cool, I guess. My
question remains, how am I going to
actually use this in Claude Design from
a process standpoint, right? So, of
course, I could go back here, and I
could start something new like a
high-fidelity, let's say, a landing
page, and I can select my design system,
which is this one. I could theoretically
design a new page on my site, but, you
know, that is in no way integrated with
my actual code base. So, I would end up
sort of in the same place that we did
before. I could maybe export the link
between Claude Design and bring it into
Claude code, and and then sort of add
some additional instructions on like,
"Hey, look at this design and adapt it,
integrate it into my code base and the
design conventions and everything." But,
that is too messy and chaotic, and it
would almost definitely result in some
spaghetti code and some bugs that would
be difficult to maintain over time. And
so, what I ended up doing is just not
using Claude Design to redesign my site.
I did it all in Claude Code, and I did
create a design system because design
systems in general are essential for,
you know, professional design,
especially if we want the branding and
everything to stay consistent as I build
out the rest of the site. So, what I did
was in my back end, so I have a custom
back end interface that I used to manage
the back end membership for Builder
Methods Pro, I added this page called
design system. And this is where I
actually define my own design system.
This is all a custom interface that I
created, or I had Claude help me create,
but it basically defines all of the
individual components that we're going
to use, you know, throughout the the
site and the application. All these
little things that I know that I'm
always going to be using whenever I'm
building out pages on my site. And I
also included actual documentation into
how each component should be coded. This
is really extensive. Like everything is
in here. All the little pages and
elements that you'll see throughout the
Builder Methods brand and website, it's
all documented in here. Now, this is
much more useful to me because it is
fully integrated into my code base.
Specifically, if I look at my claw.md
I have a bunch of stuff about my code
base, but down here I've got a whole
section. This is in claw.md which gets
baked into every prompt. So, every time
I'm having Claude work on a new part of
my application, add a new page, add a
new feature for Builder Methods Pro,
it's always going to read these design
system rules. So, right here it's
actually referencing a a markdown
version of all this, and it's always
going to reference and look for these
patterns. So, it's going to see if we
already have an existing pattern that it
can use for whatever it is that I'm
prompting to build, and if it doesn't,
then it will create or modify the the
design system and keep it all
consistent. The entire goal of this is
to reduce design drift. So, to me this
is a more professional way of
implementing a design system in a Claude
Code powered code base. You know, going
back and forth between So, here I'm back
in the Claude design app. Like again,
it's good for mock-ups and wireframes
and quick ideas, but the handoff is
still pretty disjointed. So, I'd rather
just end up working directly in Claude
Code and put the design discipline into
claw.md. So, that's where I'm going to
push back on the hype. It's not so much
about the quality, it's the process. I
just don't see how Claude design fits
into the process for a production-ready
design or application. But, there are
two ways that I am using it, and I think
that these are actually breakthroughs
that weren't really possible before.
So, I'm going to show you those now, but
first, if we haven't met yet, I'm Brian
Castle, and on this channel I help you
become a builder or adapt as a builder
using AI. And every Friday I send my
Builder Briefing. It's a free 5-minute
read, no hype, just giving you my take
on this transition to building with AI.
You can get yours by going to
buildermethods.com.
By the way, in Builder Methods Pro, I
just launched a new course called Become
the Builder. It helps you go from vibe
coding to building the way that the pros
do. You can join hundreds of other
builders in our community by going to
buildermethods.com/pro.
And most of the frustration that people
have when building with AI isn't a
failure of the models. They've actually
gotten really good. The challenge is
that it's on us to become the product
architect and clearly explain and
document what we actually want our
agents to build. And if you don't have
that experience as a product designer,
then jumping straight into plan mode
isn't really going to help. A lot of the
best shaping and planning, it happens in
that messy, meandering, exploratory
shaping phase where you're still
figuring out what you want and why you
want it and how it should feel. So, this
is where I think Claude design can be a
breakthrough for many builders,
especially if you're new to the process
of designing and building tools with AI,
because it lets you visualize your ideas
and manipulate them with a visual canvas
before you lock them into a plan or a
spec or a code base. Let me show you
what I mean.
Okay, so I'm back in Claude design, and
now let me use it as a visual planning
tool that I can use to kick off the new
ideation phase or the shaping phase for
a totally new product, because I think
it could be really helpful for that. So,
one product idea that I've had on my
shiny objects list forever is a metrics
dashboard app where I can, you know,
track my traffic and my sales and leads
and newsletter sign-ups and social media
metrics all in a single dashboard,
right? I still might build that at some
point. So, yesterday I was in here
playing around, and I started to mock up
this metrics app mock. And the way that
I started this off was a super simple
prompt, just like two sentences about,
you know, I want to create an app that
gives me a one-page metrics dashboard to
track all these different metrics, show
me the most important numbers and how
they've trended. That's all I said in in
my initial prompt. And then I went
through the question process that I
showed earlier. I answered some
questions, and and then Claude, you
know, did its thing, and it came up with
three different options for me, right?
So, I've got like an A, B, and C. And
then what what ended up happening was,
you know, C was pretty good, but I
wanted to tweak it a little bit, right?
So, I said, "Let's run with option C,
but make it cleaner, a little bit less
boxy, and more of a flat design." And
so, that's how we ended up here, right?
And I'm I'm kind of happy with this as
like an overall look and feel, but we're
still in the early visual ideation
phase. So, what I do think is useful
from here, where I can go from here, is
use this to kick off a planning phase
and a shaping phase. So, now I would
like to just export this option C, and I
don't want these earlier options, which
I'm going to sort of discard, right? So,
I could reorder these, but I didn't find
an easy way to just export this one
screen, which I thought was kind of
weird. Maybe they'll improve that pretty
soon. So, what I am going to do is I'm
just going to take a screenshot of it.
However, it is scrollable. And let's
see, I guess I could go like full
screen, but what I'm going to do is I'm
going to use one of my favorite tools
that I've used forever called CleanShot.
This is how I can get like a scrolled a
screenshot. Now, I'm done, and I can
copy that to my clipboard. And now my
next move would be not even to bring
this into Claude Code, because it is not
ready to build yet. I don't have a
product plan in place. I don't have a
spec or a PRD, but I do have a visual
that can help me and Claude get started
on a shaping phase, right? So, if I come
into my Claude account, today I'm using
Opus 4.7, which is it's great, it just
came out. So, I'm going to paste in that
screenshot. And so, now I can start a
shaping phase. And here's how I would
get started on that. I would start with
a prompt like, "Here is a rough mock-up
for a new metrics dashboard application
that I plan to build. As you can see,
the focus is on pulling together
multiple metrics from multiple data
sources into a single dashboard. I want
you to help me shape up a detailed scope
and product plan for this. Where should
we begin?" So, again, if you are totally
new to designing applications or or
designing products or creating your own
tools, this is a really simple way to
visually bring your idea to life and get
started, and then you can ask a question
like this, like, "Help me shape up a
scope and a product plan for this. Where
should we begin?" And let Claude help
you through this process, right? Now, of
course, I have some more experience in
building apps and products for many
years, so I might add, you know, some
some more questions in here like, "I
want to design and decide on the scope
in terms of which features are in scope
versus out of scope. I want to plan out
key user flows and what the user
experience is going to be. And I would
also like to make some decisions in
regards to tech stack and what is the
optimal tech stack to use. Ask me any
other questions or clarifications that
you might be helpful at this very early
stage." Okay, so, you know, here we go.
With Claude is helping me figure out
like the who and the why, and helping
me, you know, decide on some important
decisions like what counts as a source.
So, we're thinking through the entities
or the data model, if you will, starting
to really understand the architecture.
So, again, if you are lacking experience
in these types of product decisions, we
have Claude at our resource to help
bring this process into a more
professional cadence. This This is how
we actually move from just vibe coding
and hoping that it's going to build and
dream up what we are dreaming up to
actually codifying a real plan and a
real spec. Now, of course, now we're in
regular Claude, and I can export this
out into an artifact. I would typically
go back and forth 20, 30 times before I
have something really solid and shaped
and ready to bring into Claude Code and
start building, but where did we begin?
We began in Claude Design. And even just
starting with this metrics dashboard, it
helped Claude see some of the details
that I'm envisioning, right? And it
helped to inform some of these detailed
questions that Claude is asking me. So,
that to me is actually a real
breakthrough. We're on a much stronger
starting point here is what I'm trying
to say, thanks to having this, because,
you know, even someone without design
skills or frankly the time required to
go into Figma and create something as
detailed as this, this to me is a real
breakthrough for for Claude design is in
this early planning and shaping process.
Okay, now this last use case is the one
that I'm personally most excited about.
I will actually be using Claude design
for this case all the time, I think.
Now, I talked earlier about how I
created a design system for my new
Builder Methods brand design. I created
another version of the design system,
which is actually more usable for me in
Claude design, and that is a version of
the Builder Methods brand design system
that only has the colors and the font or
the typography, right? So, when I
created this one, all it has is some
type direction and the brand colors that
I'm using in the Builder Methods brand.
I don't need all the other components or
page layout stuff or, you know, an
application elements because I'm not
going to design and build actual UI here
in Claude Design, but I am going to
create other marketing assets that that
I still want to be tied into my brand
design. So, basically, when I went
through the process of creating this
design system, I gave it very specific
instructions. I said, "Because Claude
Design is going to try to create an
entire overkill design system that it's
going to give you a lot of elements that
I think, frankly, are not very usable."
So, I specifically instructed it and I
said, "I only want the typography." And
I gave it the name of the font that I'm
using, and I only want these colors, and
I just copied in my CSS from my actual
code base into it, and that's how we
defined just the type and the colors.
So, that's good to go. Now, how am I
going to actually use that and what am I
going to produce coming out of Claude
Design? Well, there are two specific use
cases that I'm definitely going to be
using it for. One is to create
animations. So, obviously, I create a
lot of videos here on the channel, and a
lot of the times the things that I
discuss are not things on screen, but I
still want to have visuals for those.
And so, I created this little test
animation, which is pretty cool. pretty
high quality, and as you can see, it is
on brand. It's using my typography, it's
using the colors that I'm using in the
new Builder Methods brand. So, you know,
this is sort of just an example, not
something real that I'm going to be
using, but I will be creating and you'll
probably start to see animations that
look like these in some of my upcoming
videos because I can, you know, bring in
some of the ideas or parts of my script
that I'm using and start to add some
pretty nice visuals into my content. By
the way, I can't believe the timing on
this, but like the week before Claude
Design dropped, I actually created a
custom application for doing exactly
that. I've been building the new course
Become the Builder that's in Builder
Methods Pro, and I wanted to create
these like animated slides for the
course that I'm building, and I created
this whole interface for doing exactly
that. And yeah, so, this is kind of
cool, too, cuz it integrates with Claude
Code, and I can prompt it, and I can
also keep a library of common elements
that I use in all of my animations. So,
that could still be useful for me, but I
must say, I ended up being a little bit
more impressed with the quality and the
animation, especially, coming out of
Claude Design. So, I think I'm probably
just going to use Claude Design. The
timing on that is unbelievable because
this dropped like days after I finished
building this whole application. So,
that's fun. And one other pretty similar
use case, I've been invited to speak at
some conferences this year on, you know,
building with AI and team adoption, and
so, you know, I need to create some
slide decks, and those two I want to
have integrated with my brand. And by
the way, a slide deck is like a
dedicated type of design that they've
built into Claude Design, and so, I did
this little test slide deck, and as you
can see, you know, again, it keeps my
brand design intact. These are pretty
high quality, clean layouts for the
slide deck. And I also really like that
they built in a feature to have speaker
notes. So, when I am presenting this,
whether it's at a conference or one of
the workshops that I do for Builder
Methods Pro, I can have a separate
screen showing my my speaker notes or
the slides, and they even have present,
you know, I can go full screen and and
all that. So, this is actually very
useful, right? So, this is outside of my
code base, but these are marketing
assets for videos or slide decks that
still need to be on brand, and Claude
Design is sort of a perfect tool for
that use case. So, here's how I'd frame
Claude Design right now. It's not an
idea-to-ship tool, and it's not a design
layer for your existing code base, but
it is genuinely useful for creating
on-brand marketing assets. And I think
it's especially useful during that
earliest shaping phase for a new
product. Now, the question is, how do
you take that raw mock-up and get to a
ready-to-build spec? Well, I made a new
video on how I run that shaping phase,
and it's a skill that I don't think AI
will ever be able to replace. So, first,
hit subscribe so you don't miss my next
video, and then I'll see you over there
next. Let's keep building.